Ehsan-Ul Haq

Ph.D.
Computer Science and Engineering
The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, HKSAR

Email: euhaq@connect.ust.hk Google Scholar 🗹 LinkedIn 🖸

RESEARCH AREAS

My research area spans Computational Social Science and Human-Computer Interaction. I am interested in information polarization and information diffusion in online networks concerning offline events. In particular, I work on users' behaviour characterization and their utilization of the systems. I work on data from online social networks and discussion forums. Apart from the research, I also have experience in teaching courses like Computer Programming and Social Networks Analysis, supervision of undergraduate final-year projects, and working in the IT industry as an iOS developer.

EDUCATION

Ph.D.	The Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, HKSAR	2017-2023
M.S.	Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russia,	2013-2015
	Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, USA	Exchange Student, 2014
B.S.	National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences, Islamabad, Pakistan cum laude ,	2007-2011

PUBLICATIONS

Articles in Peer-Reviewed Journals

- Ehsan-Ul Haq, Tristan Braud, Young D. Kwon, Pan Hui "A Survey on Computational Politics" *IEEE Access, vol.* 8, pp. 197379-197406, 2020, doi:10.1109/ACCESS.2020.3034983
- Dimitris Chatzopoulos, Carlos Bermejo, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Yong Li and Pan Hui "D2D Task Offloading: A Dataset-Based QA" *IEEE Communications Magazine*, vol. 57, no. 2, pp. 102-107, February 2019 doi:10.1109/MCOM.2018.1700873

Conference Proceedings

- 2022 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Yang K. Lu, and Pan Hui "It's all Relative! A Method to Counter Human Bias in Crowdsourced Stance Detection of News Articles" In Proceedings of the 25th ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2022), Taipei Taiwan, November 2022
- 2022 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Lik-Hang Lee, Gareth Tyson, Reza Hadi Mogavi, Tristan Braud, and Pan Hui "Exploring Mental Health Communications among Instagram Coaches" In the Proceedings of International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM'2022), Istanbul, Turkey
- Ehsan-Ul Haq, Gareth Tyson, Tristan Braud, and Pan Hui "Weaponising Social Media for Information Divide and Warfare" In Proceedings of the 33rd ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media (HT'22). Barcelona, Spain, June 2022. Blue Sky Awards, Third Prize
- Ehsan-Ul Haq, Tristan Braud, Lik Hang Lee, Reza Hadi Mogavi, He Zhang, Pan Hui "Tips, Tidings, and Tech: Governmental Communication on Facebook During the COVID-19 Pandemic" dg.o 2022: 23rd Annual International Conference on Digital Government Research. South Korea, June 15-17, 2022. (to appear soon)
- Reza Hadi Mogavi, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Sujit Gujar, Pan Hui, and Xiaojuan Ma. More Gamification Is Not Always Better: A Case Study of Promotional Gamification in a Question Answering Website. In Proceedings of the 25th ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2022), Taipei Taiwan, November 2022.

- Reza Hadi Mogavi, Yuanhao Zhang, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Yongjin Wu, Pan Hui, and Xiaojuan Ma. What Do Users Think of Promotional Gamification Schemes? A Qualitative Case Study in a Question Answering Website. In Proceedings of the 25th ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW 2022), Taipei Taiwan, November 2022.
- Reza Hadi Mogavi, Bingcan Guo, Yuanhao Zhang, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Pan Hui, and Xiaojuan Ma "When Gamification Spoils Your Learning: A Qualitative Case Study of Gamification Misuse in a Language-Learning App." In Proceedings of the 9th ACM Conference on Learning at Scale (L@S) Conference 2022, Roosevelt Island, New York City, USA, June 2022.(to appear soon)
- 2022 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Tristan BRAUD, Yui-Pan YAU, Lik Hang LEE, Franziska KELLER and Pan HUI "The role of Instagram for Social Activism: A case study on Hong Kong Protests" In the Proceedings of ACM Web Conference, Lyon, France 2022 (WWW-2022)
- Ehsan-Ul Haq, Tristan Braud, Lik Hang Lee, Anish Krishna Vallapuram, Yue Yu, Gareth Tyson and Pan Hui "Short, Colorful, and Irreverent! A Comparative Analysis of New Users on WallstreetBets During the Gamestop Short-squeeze" In the Proceedings of ACM Web Conference, Lyon, France 2022 (WWW-2022)
- Reza Hadi Mogavi, Yankun Zhao, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Pan Hui, Xiaojuan Ma "Student Barriers to Active Learning in Synchronous Online Classes: Characterization, Reflections, and Suggestions." In the Proceedings of 8th ACM Conference on Learning@ Scale (L@S2021), Germany, June 23-25, 2021
- 2020 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Tristan Braud, Young D. Kwon, Pan Hui "Enemy at the Gate: Evolution of Twitter User's Polarization During National Crisis" the Proceedings of International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM'2020).
- 2020 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Tristan Braud, Pan Hui "Community Matters more than Anonymity: Analysis of User Interactions on the Quora Q&A Platform" the Proceedings of International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM'2020).
- Young D. Kwon, Dimitris Chatzopoulos, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Raymond Chi-Wing Wong, and Pan Hui "GeoLifecycle: User Engagement of Geographical Exploration and Churn Prediction in LBSNs" *IMWUT 2019*.
- Young D. Kwon, Reza Hadi Mogavi, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Youngjin Kwon, Xiaojuan Ma, and Pan Hui "Effects of Ego Networks and Communities on Self-Disclosure in an Online Social Network" *In the Proceedings of International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM'2019)*, Vancouver, Canada

Dataset Papers

- 2022 **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Gareth Tyson, Lik-Hang Lee, Tristan Braud, Pan Hui "Twitter dataset for 2022 russo-ukrainian crisis" arXiv preprint arXiv:2203.02955
- 2022 Yiming ZHU, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Gareth TYSON, and Pan HUI. "A Reddit Dataset for the Russo-Ukrainian Conflict in 2022" arXiv preprint arXiv:2206.05107

Technical/Policy Reports

Franziska Keller, Pan Hui, Tristan Braud, **Ehsan-Ul Haq**, Ting Yin NG, Hanying Wei "The spread of rumors on and across social media platforms during Hong Kong's anti-extradition-law-protests", November 2020 A public policy report for Hong Kong Government

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Hong Kong University of Sciecne and Technology, Hong Kong (SAR)

I have worked as teaching assistant for the following courses during my PhD.

COMP 4641: Social Network Analysis and Engineering [Spring 2020, Spring 2021]

COMP 1001: Exploring Multimedia and Internet Computing [Fall 2019]

COMP 3311: Database Management System [Spring 2019, Fall 2018, Spring 2018, Fall 2017]

National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences, Islamabad, Pakistan

I have worked as lecturer and taught the following courses at undergraduate level:

Human Computer Interaction

Computer Programming

Data Structures and Algorithms

Data warehouse

SKILLS/TOOLS

Python, R, Data Visualization(Gephi), iOS development

Data Collection (Web Scrapping and APIs) / Qualitative Data Collection and Analysis

Data Management - large scale data processing, storage, and anonymization

SERVICE

Reviewer for the following conferences/journals

ICWSM - International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media

IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Science - IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Science

ACM CHI - Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems

IEEE COMMAG - IEEE Communication Magazine

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

[Jun 2014–Aug 2014] **Intern**

Google Inc, Moscow, Russia

A two months internship involved an introduction to Google Chromium and fuzzing methodologies, it required writing fuzzer programs to test the chromium for bugs

[Mar 2012–Aug 2013] **Business Solutions Analyst** Converge Enterprise Services, Islamabad, Pakistan My primary role was as an iOS developer and coordinating requirement elicitation.

- -IntelliOps Operational/Corporate Performance (iPad) (Winner at SAP Insider event 2012) The IntelliOps app is specially designed for large industries. It has two versions for corporate and operational performance measurement. It interacts with SAP through the Sybase mobility platform and represents statistical data about different units in industries in the form of charts, graphs, gauges and alerts.
- **IntelliOps LUBEREF** A version of IntelliOps Operational Performance with enhanced features for the oil and gas industry, specifically designed for LUBEREF Saudi Arabia.
- **Al-Majdouie Employee Management Application** An in-house app for employee management, racking leaves records, pay slips, and notifications.

[Jul 2011–Mar 2012] **Software Engineer**

Coeus Solutions GmbH, Lahore, Pakistan

My primary role was as an iOS developer.

- **Qype** (*Acquired by Yelp*) A location-based services app for the iOS platform for review sharing and social updates. I worked on three different versions: 3.2, 3.5, and 4.0.

Honors and Awards

2017 Post Graduate Scholarship for Ph.D at HKUST
 2014 Semi Finalist, MIT 100K Competition, MIT, USA
 2013-2015 Fellowship at Skolkovo for MS Program in IT, Moscow, Russia

2014 Exchange Student at MIT

2007-2011 Dean's List of Honor during undergraduate degree

2007-2011 Scholarship on merit for BS degree sponsored by IT Ministry, Pakistan